The island of Cuba is currently facing
the worst existential crisis that it has
ever faced in its history. You've maybe
missed what's going on here with all the
other chaotic things going on in the
news right now. But over the past 5
years, Cuba has witnessed the most rapid
population collapse that any society has
experienced so far in the 21st century.
At the start of the decade in 2020, Cuba
was reported to have had a population of
around 11.2 million people. Since then,
it's been estimated by independent
observers that as many as 2.75 million
Cubans have left the island, meaning
that nearly 1 in every four Cubans have
probably left the country in only 5
years. An utterly catastrophic emptying
out of the island's people. The Cuban
government itself officially claims a
much lower number of people who have
left since 2020. But even their own
likely downplayed data claims that 14%
of the island's population have left the
country over these past 5 years. Even if
that official data was true, it would
already be the second fastest rate of
population decline experienced by any
country in the world this decade, only
behind the rate experienced in Ukraine,
a country that has been actively at war
for years and being massively invaded by
its neighbor. [music] If the official
data is already that bad, the truth is
probably much worse and closer to the
independent analyses that are being
done. The Cuban government now
officially claims that the population on
the island has shrunk from 11.2 million
people in 2020 to around 9.7 million
people as of the start of 2026.
While the independent analysis conducted
by Juan Carlos Elzibu Campos, a leading
Cuban demographer, estimates that it's
actually probably declined closer to
around 8.25 million people instead. One
of the biggest things that all of these
people have been fleeing from has been a
similarly rapidly collapsing economy.
Since 2018, the Cuban economy has
declined by at least 15%.
And that's according to official Cuban
government data. Since the CO 19
pandemic began, inflation in the country
has absolutely skyrocketed. In 2019, the
Cuban peso traded at a value of 20 to1
to the US dollar. But by November of
2025, it was trading at 450 to1 to the
US dollar at the informal rate instead,
implying an annualized inflation rate of
around 68% every year for six [music]
straight years, which has been verging
on hyperinflation and wrecking Cuban
savings. The Cuban Observatory for Human
Rights, an NGO based abbron in [music]
Spain, has recently estimated that an
astonishing 89% of the Cuban population
now lives in extreme poverty, while 7
out of 10 Cubans are having to skip at
least one meal per day. Only 3% are
capable of finding the medicine that
they require atarmacies. 12% of the
working age population is presently
unemployed, while a whopping 78% of
Cubans they surveyed reported that they
either wanted to leave the country
themselves or knew someone else who did.
Wages and the cost of living in Cuba
have gotten to a point where life on the
island is almost impossible for the vast
majority of people. The official average
monthly wage in Cuba based on the
government's own data is just 6,56
pesos a month, which is about the same
as just a little over 14 US a month at
the informal [music] rate. And yet, a
carton of 30 eggs on the island
currently cost 2,800 pesos, equivalent
to 43% of the average monthly wage. Even
a kilo of rice and a kilo of beans, the
typical staple diet in Cuba, currently
cost the average worker in the country
about three full days worth of their
labor. Gasoline shortages across the
island have become chronic and too
expensive for most to afford. as well.
Drivers frequently have to wait weeks
now just in order to acquire a rationed
allocation [music] of 40 L or 10 1/2
gallons of gas that now costs about 46
US, which is usually several times their
own typical monthly wage. The highways
across the country have emptied out.
People in the rural countryside beyond
the big cities have gone back to using
horsedrawn carriages and carts because
of the lack of fuel. While public
transportation, even within the big
cities, has effectively grinded to a
halt, there is also an increasingly
chronic electricity and energy shortage
that has been suffocating the island as
well. Mass blackouts have become routine
occurrences since [music] 2020. With no
fewer than five nationwide blackouts
taking place just across [music] 2025,
during the blistering heat of the
summer, electricity across most of the
island will flicker off for at least 4
hours a day. Now, while some of the
lesser populated provinces outside of
the major cities can sometimes go up to
20 hours a day without power, affecting
everything from air conditioning to fans
to refrigerators,
Cuba is currently producing about 25%
less power than it did just 6 years ago
back in 2019, based on research
published by Ricardo Torres, a Cuban
economist affiliated with the American
University, which is why the blackouts
sweeping across the island have been
increasing. in frequency. The big reason
why is because the vast majority of
Cuba's electricity is generated by oil
with outdated and worn out Soviet era
diesel generators. While the island's
imports of oil have been dwindling and
dwindling, roughly 83% of Cuba's
electricity is generated through burning
oil at these diesel plants, while 60% of
Cuba's oil demand has to be imported
from abroad. Historically, until very
recently, Venezuela was providing Cuba
with the lion's share of its imported
oil supply that it needed to keep the
lights on. In 2021, Venezuela was
providing Cuba with more than 100,000
barrels of oil per day, enough to
satisfy about 80% of their domestic
needs and more than they actually
needed. But as Venezuela's own economic
crisis began getting worse, their
exports of oil to Cuba declined by
nearly 34s to only 16,000 [music]
barrels of oil per day by 2025.
And now, after the US military captured
Venezuela's president through a raid in
early January, the Trump administration
is threatening to sever even this last
drip of oil that's coming into the
country, too, threatening even more oil
shortages and blackouts on the island in
the near future. Since capturing
Venezuela's president, the Trump
administration has been clear in their
threats that the communist regime in
Cuba could well be next. Within hours of
the raid that captured Maduro, Trump and
his secretary of state, Marco Rubio,
himself, the son of Cuban exiles, had
this to say.
>> So, uh, yeah, Cuba really isn't in a
good spot right [music] now. And with an
aggressive US government breathing down
their neck after the successful Maduro
operation in Venezuela, a lot of
analysts have started predicting that
the communist regime on the island in
power continually for the past 67 years
is now the closest it has ever been to
finally collapsing, accomplishing one of
the United States's longest held
geopolitical goals for decades. But
people have also been predicting the
Communist Party's imminent collapse in
Cuba for a long, long time now. At least
going back to the end of the Cold War
when the Soviet Union collapsed in the
early 1990s.
And yet, it's always somehow managed to
endure and hang on despite all of these
outside people's expectations.
The Communist Party's [music] control of
Cuba has made it a thorn in the side of
America for generations now. the
successive president after president
since the Eisenhower administration has
never been able to solve. The island is
essentially one of the final remaining
relics of the Cold War [music] that's
still left behind in the world today,
including its tense relationship with
the United States. Cuba is arguably the
only true surviving Marxist Leninist
state left over from the Cold War that
never collapsed or significantly pivoted
its ideology in the same kind of way
that other surviving states that claim
to be communist today did like North
Korea which went down the radical path
of its own unique ju nationalist
ideology or China, Vietnam and Laos
which have all adopted significant
economic and free market reforms that
have introduced vibrant private
businesses that Cuba has still never
done in resistance. did. And all of this
is despite the fact that the world's
last pure Marxist Leninist state exists
just 90 miles away from the most
capitalistic country on Earth, the
United States, who has been embargoing
all trade with Cuba and sanctioning
[music] it for decades now. In order for
you to understand how Cuba got to what
is potentially the brink of collapse
today, why the relationship between Cuba
and the United States has remained so
tense, even this long after the end of
the Cold War, and how the orthodox
communist regime in Cuba has somehow
managed to survive against all of the
odds into the present day and defied
everybody's previous predictions of
collapse and why this time might
actually finally be different. It helps
to begin with just a little bit of
backstory.
Immediately before the communist
revolution took place in Cuba, the
country was ruled by this authoritarian
dictator known as Fulgensio Batista, who
was genuinely widely unpopular and also
backed by the United States because he
did America's bidding, often to the
detriment of his own people. Batista was
a colonel in the Cuban armed forces who
served as the president of Cuba once
between 1940 and 1944 and then ran again
for a second term in 1952. When he faced
almost certain defeat in that second
election, he launched a military coup
and [music] seized power through force
instead. After which he almost
immediately suspended the Cuban
Constitution and revoked most of the
country's civil liberties, including the
right for anyone to strike. then in
order to shore up his shaky and
illegitimate position. But he still
aligned himself closely to the US
government as a foreign benefactor along
with Cuba's own wealthy landowning
elites who owned the island's largest
sugar plantations which was Cuba's
number one trading commodity for
centuries. Batista was also very closely
connected to the American mafia and in
exchange for bribes he basically gave
taxexempt [music]
status to mafio owned casinos,
racetracks, brothel and nightclubs
across the country which was an open
secret across Cuban society throughout
the later 1950s.
[music] Eventually, due to him basically
opening up the entire country to the
Americans and other foreigners in
exchange for blatant personal bribes, it
reached a point under his rule where
about 70% of all the arable land in the
country was owned by foreigners,
including most of the island's most
valuable asset, its sugar plantations.
And perhaps the most infamous example of
Batista's personal corruption and
openness of bribes while he was
dictator. An American telephone
conglomerate literally presented him
with a golden telephone during a
ceremony to thank him for raising the
prices of telephone usage within Cuba to
ridiculous levels. Batista was openly
willing to be personally bribed and
enriched in exchange for making his
fellow Cubans have to pay more for basic
services provided by American companies.
enduring him with absolutely zero
loyalty from his own people and
consistently making him appear to be
nothing but a corporate Americanbacked
stoogge [music] to most.
As his unpopularity grew within Cuba,
Batista consistently [music] and
increasingly resorted to the military
censorship and repression to keep the
Cuban people's anger under control,
[music]
even establishing his own secret police
force that conducted massive violence,
torture, and even public executions.
Throughout Batista's dictatorial rule,
it's believed that up to 20,000 Cubans
were killed while countless others were
jailed or tortured. And throughout all
of this, the US government appeared
indifferent to the suffering of the
Cuban people so long as they got what
they wanted out of Cuba economically.
Throughout Batista's rule in Cuba, there
was a saying that the US ambassador was
the second most powerful man on the
island. He effectively controlled the
flow of arms to Batista's regime, which
he needed in order to repress his own
people and defend his position of power.
In exchange for increasing the US arms
deliveries, the ambassador would demand
more generous conditions for US
businesses on the island. Batista along
with his backers in Washington were so
repressive and unpopular in Cuba that
large segments of the population began
turning to the radical revolution being
led by Fidel Castro and Shau Var and
their gorillas as a solution to their
plight instead. On the final day of the
year in 1958, Castro's revolution was
finally successful and Batista fled the
country on New Year's Day of 1959 for
the Dominican Republic, which at the
time was ruled by fellow US backed
right-wing dictator Raphael Trujillo.
Along with him, Batista also paged most
of the Cuban treasury's assets to the
tune of as much as $700 million worth of
cash and fine art, which immediately
kneecapped Castro's incoming
revolutionary government that overthrew
[music] him. Nonetheless, Castro was
dramatically popular with most of the
Cuban people at the time, both for
having overthrown the oppressive and
hated Batista regime and for his own
personal charisma and sense of presence.
Many of Cuba's old elites who were close
to the Batista regime immediately began
fleeing the country, [music]
especially to South Florida. While
Castro himself initially insisted that
his revolution was not actually
communist in nature, attempting instead
to present at least a nominal
restoration of democracy in Cuba.
Nonetheless, the US government was still
intensely worried about what Castro's
rise to power in Cuba meant for their
lucrative and exploitative business
interests on the island. So, the
Eisenhower administration began
preparing the top secret Bay of Pigs
invasion operation to use CIA trained
Cuban exile anti-Castro paramilitaries
to invade the island and topple Castro,
ideally from Washington's perspective,
enabling them to claim at least some
degree of plausible deniability.
A few months after the Bay of Pigs plan
began being set into motion,
American-owned oil refineries on Cuba
refused to accept Castro's demand that
they begin processing oil from the
Soviet Union, which led to Castro
nationalizing and expropriating their
assets over the summer of 1960, which
led to the US halting their imports of
Cuba's sugar, which led to Castro
retaliating by nationalizing even more
US-owned assets in the country in a
spiraling tit fortat trade war. After
JFK assumed the presidency in early
1961, he inherited the Eisenhower
administration's planning for the Bay of
Pigs operation, which he decided to
ultimately authorize in April of that
year, a few months later, and which
would quickly prove to be a catastrophic
overplaying of Washington's own hand.
The day before the roughly 1,000man
strong force of Cuban exile
paramilitaries hit the beach in Cuba,
the US Air Force began bombing strategic
Cuban airfields in order to weaken their
defenses. and Castro finally publicly
declared himself a Marxist Leninist for
the first time in response. The next
day, the Cuban exile paramilitary
stormed the beaches at the Bay of Pigs.
But in order for the whole plan to work,
it required the aerial support of the US
Air Force, which never ended up
materializing after it almost
immediately began going very badly for
them, undermining Washington's own goal
of maintaining plausible deniability.
The entire invasion force was either
killed or captured. And the hundreds who
were taken prisoner were taken to a
sports stadium in Havana where they were
publicly and flamboyantly interrogated
and heranged by Castro himself on live
television. All of which simply ended up
skyrocketing Castro's popularity in Cuba
as a symbol of resistance against
American imperialism. All the Bay of
Pigs invasion ended up doing was to
rapidly speed up Cuba's transformation
into a Marxist Leninist one party state
and push it directly into the lap of the
Soviet Union. Because almost immediately
after it, Castro had both the legitimacy
and the power to declare the country a
socialist state that would no longer
hold any open elections. And this right
here is part of how the Communist Party
of Cuba has managed to hang on a power
in Cuba for decades longer than nearly
every other communist regime was capable
[music] of. In countries across Eastern
Europe, like East Germany or Poland or
Romania, their communist governments
were forced upon them by an outside
invader, the Soviet Union. By contrast,
Cuba's communist revolution was the
result of an entirely natural domestic
homegrown popular revolution that almost
immediately gained strong legitimacy
after the US government instantly and
clumsily began attacking it in order to
maintain their privileged and
exploitative business interests on the
island. [music]
Of course, forever since then, relations
between Cuba and the United States have
remained extremely negative and tense.
[music] The US government severed its
relations with Cuba the same year as the
Bay of Pigs incident in 1961. And then
in the following year, the US declared a
full [music] and comprehensive trade
embargo against Cuba that has blocked
virtually all imports and exports
between the two nations ever since with
the sole exceptions being on food,
medicine, and humanitarian goods.
running continually for the past 64
years now, even for decades after the
Cold War ended, it has evolved into the
longest running trade embargo of modern
history, and has contributed greatly to
the crushing of the Cuban economy. Since
the Cold War ended, and starting in
1992, the UN General Assembly has voted
no less than 33 consecutive times every
single year to adopt a resolution
calling for the US to finally end its
embargo on Cuba. The US naturally has
simply voted against the resolution
every single time. Though during the
most recent vote in October of 2025,
165 of the UN member states voted in
favor of the resolution. While the US
along with key allies like Israel,
Ukraine, Argentina, Hungary, Paraguay,
and North Macedonia were the only ones
to vote against it. The Cuban government
and the UN have officially estimated
that over its entire length of more than
six decades now, the embargo has
inflicted between 130 and 148 billion US
in cumulative damage to the island's
economy, and it has continually been
used as a tool by the US government to
try and pressure regime change. In 1963,
following all of the drama associated
with the Cuban missile crisis, the US
government also froze all of Cuba's
assets in the United States and outlawed
virtually all financial transactions
between the two countries as well. Being
completely blocked off from the US and
its global alliance system, Cuba needed
an outside patron in order to survive.
And for decades until the end of the
Cold War, that outside patron was the
Soviet Union, who provided cheap
subsidized oil to Cuba that they could
use for fuel and electricity, while Cuba
provided the Soviet Union with cheap
sugar and a strategic foothold in the
Western Hemisphere [music] to project
power from. Only 90 m away from the US
mainland. Castro's Marxist Leninist
regime in Cuba, while authoritarian and
undemocratic, was also capable of
accomplishing some great things on the
island. They were able to rapidly
improve the literacy rate in Cuba from
only about 68% when they took over to
96% within only a couple of years. They
also implemented a state-run universal
health care system free to all Cuban
residents with well-trained doctors and
the highest number of doctors per capita
in the entire world which eventually
evolved into an influence engine of the
Castros of their own as they could
export their well-trained doctors and
medical brigades abroad in exchange for
resources they needed like oil, food,
and medicine back home that they
couldn't get from the United States. At
the same time, however, that doesn't
mean that there weren't also a lot of
people in Cuba who were pissed off at
the new system of government. Castro
seized and nationalized tens of
thousands of small private businesses
across the country, effectively outlawed
all private businesses and enterprises
and redistributed the large agricultural
lands and estates that were owned by the
prior wealthy elites and foreigners.
Unlike other communist leaders in places
like East Germany and North Korea that
strictly didn't allow any of their
citizens to leave, Fidel from time to
time actually allowed waves of
disgruntled Cubans who were angry with
his way of governance to leave the
island as a sort of blowoff valve to
relieve pressure and reduce the internal
resistance to his government, filtering
out the island's demographics to being
mostly loyalists who still remained. In
the immediate aftermath of the
revolution's success in 1959, an
estimated 250,000
Cubans, most of them disgruntled former
business owners and land owners who were
associated with the former Batista
regime, left the island within a few
years by 1962. Most of them across the
Florida Straight to Miami and the South
Florida region more broadly. Then
between 1965 and 1973, the US government
organized the so-called freedom flights
between Cuba and Miami, a program that
was funded by the United States and
authorized by Castro that flew hundreds
of chartered flights full of additional
Cubans who wanted to migrate to the
United States. [music]
Over the years that the Freedom Flights
ran for, an estimated 300,000 additional
Cubans [music] were flown out of the
country and into Miami and South
Florida, who were all granted expedited
pathways to US citizenship after they
lived in the country for just a single
year. All of this mass migration of
Cuban exiles who were disaffected with
the communist regime on the island into
South Florida permanently altered the
region's demographic trajectory to this
day. And it's why there can sort of be
an argument that there are in reality
two different Cubas today. The Cuba on
the island of Cuba and the new Cuba in
South Florida. And there have been many,
many additional waves of Cuban migration
to South Florida since the 1960s and 70s
as well. In 1980, following a downturn
in the Cuban economy, thousands of
Cubans attempted to gain asylum status
by taking refuge on the grounds of the
Peruvian embassy in Havana, which led to
Fidel announcing that anyone who wanted
to leave the country could do so freely.
The Cuban-American community in South
Florida then assembled a hastily put
together flotilla and began fing
thousands of Cubans to America from the
island's Mariel Harbor, which gave this
particular exodus its name, the Mariel
Bole lift. Finel is also known to have
opened up his prisons and mental
institutions during this specific exodus
and sent thousands of prisoners and
patients he didn't want along with the
rest who were all taken into South
Florida by the boat lift along with
thousands of others who wanted to leave
for economic or political reasons.
Within a few months another 125,000 more
Cubans were transported to the Miami
area before the US and Cuban governments
mutually agree to put a stop to it. All
of this history of Cuban migration into
South Florida has since made it the most
Cuban area in the world anywhere outside
of the island of Cuba itself. Today,
roughly 2 million people in the Miami
metropolitan area are of Cuban ancestry.
They're the largest single ethnic group
present in the Miami area now, and they
make up about a third of Miami's total
population. When you consider that
Habana itself has an estimated
metropolitan population of around 2.15
million people now, the Cuban population
in Miami is actually about the same
size. And since Miami's Cuban population
is growing faster than Havana's is, it's
conceivable soon that Miami will
actually become the largest Cuban city
in the world. When you further consider
this more recent population exodus from
Cuba that's been happening since 2020,
South Florida as a broad region now has
about a quarter of the same Cuban
population as the island of Cuba itself
has. [music]
Which is why I said earlier that South
Florida has basically become a second
Cuba. And it's through this lens that I
would argue that the Cubans are one of
the world's peoples that were also
divided along ideological and political
lines during the Cold War. like the
Germans, Koreans, and Vietnamese all
were as well. And just like those other
peoples, the Cubans became divided
between a hyper communist system on the
island of Cuba and a hyper capitalist
system in their enclave in South
Florida. One of Miami's nicknames today
is the capital of Latin America. And
there's a lot of good points of evidence
to back that claim up. Because of the
large Cuban population in Miami and
other Latino groups, around 70% of the
city's population [music] speaks Spanish
as their primary language, which makes
Miami the only one of America's [music]
top 10 largest metropolitan areas that
is both majority Spanish-sp speakaking
and ethnically Latino. Miami also has by
far the largest GDP and economy of any
majority Spanish-sp speakaking city in
the world today, giving it the
legitimate authority to claim the title
as the Spanish-sp speakaking world's
most economically valuable city. Miami,
all on its own, currently has more than
double the GDP of the entire island of
Cuba combined, and it's arguably
becoming the most capitalistic city, not
just in Latin America, but even in the
United States. Since 2020, the Miami
area has gained another nickname, Wall
Street South, because of all of the New
York City-based financial companies and
institutions that have relocated or
shifted their operations there due to
the lower taxes and more
businessfriendly environment. It's been
estimated that more than $1 trillion
worth of assets have been shifted from
New York City to Miami just since 2020,
including the headquarter relocations of
more than 50 major investment firms. And
a big part of why that's been happening
is the foundation of Miami as a bastion
of exiles from Cuba, who happened to be
the most capitalistic minded Cubans who
left the communist system on the island
over generations and made Miami
basically the capitalist alternative to
the island of Cuba in the same way that
West Germany was to East Germany or
South Korea still is to North Korea.
When the Soviet Union suddenly collapsed
in 1991, the communist regime in Cuba
lost their historical benefactor and
supporter and entered into what the
government has called the special period
throughout the 1990s. In a flash, Cuba
lost all of their Soviet era subsidies
and privileged oil imports that have
been propping up the economy for
decades, which led to their imports and
exports crashing by more than 80% and
their economy losing about a third of
its value over just a couple of years by
1993.
Then, as now, there was a lot of
speculation that this was inevitably
going to become the end of communism on
the island. In 1994, in the midst of
this crisis over a period of 5 weeks
during particularly intense rioting in
Cuba, Fidel once again announced that
anybody who wanted to leave the country
could do so freely without hindrance,
which triggered another mass exodus of
around 35,000 Cubans who assembled
makeshift rafts and attempted to float
over the Florida straight to America.
This exodus ultimately became a sort of
turning point in America's relationship
with Cuban exiles and refugees.
Struggling to deal with the political
consequences of this particular exodus,
the Clinton administration reformed
America's migration policy regarding
Cuba through the new wet feet, dry feet
policy, which set it so that Cubans
caught in the waters by the Coast Guard
between the two countries would be
summarily returned back to Cuba or sent
to a third country. While Cubans who
made it to the shore on land in the US
would receive a chance to stay in the US
and pursue permanent residency and
citizenship following a year's time.
Conflict between the Cuban and US
governments reached a new high point
throughout the 1990s as well, where the
Cold War effectively never ended like it
did in most other parts of the world. In
1996, an organization made up of
Cuban-American exiles in South Florida
called Brothers to the Rescue were using
small private Cesta aircraft to take
flights over Cuba to drop anti-Castro
propaganda leaflets across the island.
In February of that year, a Cuban Air
Force Mig 29 fighter aircraft shot down
two unarmed Cestnas that were taking
part in one of these operations, [music]
killing all four of the Cuban-American
exile participants who were on board and
sharply spiking tensions in the process.
Then the next year in 1997, an
anti-communist militia of Cuban-American
exiles based in South Florida organized
a series of bombing attacks against
various hotels in Havana in an attempt
to undermine Cuba's resurgent tourism
industry. One foreign tourist from Italy
was killed in the bombings and 11 others
were wounded. A man named Louise Pada
Curilles later admitted to having
organized the bombings, a Cubaname exile
and former CIA officer. Pada had also
previously helped organize the Bay of
Pigs invasion in 1961 and was widely
considered to have been responsible for
the bombing of a Cuban commercial
airliner back in 1976 that had killed 73
people on board. And he was later
briefly jailed in Panama in 2000 for
allegedly plotting an assassination
attempt on Castro. In 2005, Pada entered
the US under a false passport and was
granted political asylum status, which
further strained tensions as the Cuban
government consistently requested his
extradition to stand trial in Cuba,
which the US consistently rejected until
Pada died peacefully at old age at 90
years old in 2018.
And then in 1998, five Cuban
intelligence officers were arrested by
American authorities in Miami on charges
of espionage, who later became known as
the Cuban 5. After consistently denying
that the captured men were intelligence
agents, the Cuban government finally
acknowledged them 3 years later in 2001,
claiming that they were only spying on
the Cuban-American exile community in
South Florida rather than on the US
government itself. Most of the men would
be held in prison for the next decade
and a half until the Obama
administration later negotiated a
prisoner exchange for them with the
Cuban government. And all the while, the
US trade embargo on Cuba continued as
Cuba floundered around trying to find
new trade partners to replace the Soviet
Union in the Eastern Block with. Near
the end of the decade in 1998, the
communist regime in Cuba finally gained
a new lifeline after Hugo Chavez and his
socialist party won the presidential
election in Venezuela. Quickly stepping
up to largely fill in the gap that was
left behind by the Soviets. Chavez's
administration in Venezuela began
supplying Cuba with a new source of
heavily subsidized oil again in exchange
for thousands of doctors with Cuba's
well-trained medical brigades along with
their intelligence and security services
both to help spy on their own people and
to guard their leadership. At the peak
of this cooperation between the two
countries between 2008 and 2015,
Venezuela was supplying Cuba with
approximately 100,000 barrels of
subsidized oil per day. that met more
than half of Cuba's oil import needs and
underpinned Cuba's faltering electricity
generation and industrial output. While
nearly 30,000 well-trained Cuban doctors
and medical technicians served in
Venezuela, Cuba also gained the
capability to resell the subsidized oil
that they were receiving from Venezuela
to China for higher prices than what
they had paid for it, which gave them a
rare avenue to acquire hard foreign
currency in defiance of the US financial
and trade sanctions that were still
placed upon them. And meanwhile,
tensions between Cuba and the United
States remained locked in the old Cold
War mentality throughout the Clinton and
George W. Bush administrations until,
for a brief moment, things looked like
they might finally begin changing after
decades during the later years of the
Obama administration. In December of
2014, Obama and communist Cuba's second
president, Raul Castro, Fidel's younger
brother, who had taken over in 2006
after Fidel grew ill, shocked the world
with a dual announcement on television
that Cuba and the United States would be
fully restoring diplomatic ties again
for the first time since the 1960s.
While all of his predecessors had
demanded immediate political and
economic concessions from the Communist
Party of Cuba in exchange for a
normalization of ties, which were always
refused, Obama was the first US
president who calculated instead that
immediately establishing closer
economic, cultural, and political ties
with Cuba, even without any upfront
concessions from the Communist Party,
would gradually result in a moderation
of the Communist Party's platform over
the long haul. Anyway, almost
immediately after their joint address,
both countries reopened their embassies
for the first time in 53 years. A few
months later, in 2015, Obama removed
Cuba from America's state sponsors of
terrorism list. And in 2016, he loosened
up US restrictions on Americans ability
to travel to Cuba, enabling US airlines
to resume regular air service to the
island and for US cruise ships to port
in Cuban harbors, which all opened up a
massive surge in US tourism to Cuba
again and a big new source of foreign
currency for both the government and
small local entrepreneurs like taxi
drivers and restaurant tours who began
catering to them. in just a single year
in 2015. Because of all of this, Cuba's
economy grew by more than 4%. And it was
a boon for US businesses as well. For a
couple of years, Cuba was one of
Airbnb's fastest growing markets, while
executives from Marriott and PayPal
accompanied Obama's personal visit to
Cuba in March of 2016 when he became the
first sitting US president to visit the
island in 88 years. Obama's opening up
to Cuba was massively popular with both
Cubans and the broader American public.
But as it would turn out, this new
policy would only end up lasting for a
couple of years because the successor to
the US presidency, Donald Trump, would
effectively end and reverse everything.
For Trump, railing against Obama's
friendly policies towards Cuba and
promising to reverse them was a campaign
tactic to appeal to conservative
Cuban-American voters in South Florida,
a demographic long opposed to the
continuation of communist rule in their
ancestral homeland, both for ideological
reasons and also because much of their
or their ancestors property had been
expropriated and seized following the
revolution that they wanted to be fairly
compensated for. Many high-profile
Cuban-American politicians like Marco
Rubio and Ted Cruz were staunchly
opposed to the Obama administration's
policies of openness with the regime in
Cuba without demanding any major
political concessions from them. And
Trump's strategy of attempting to appeal
to their demographic in the 2016
election ultimately proved to be highly
successful for him as 54% of the
Cuban-American voters in Florida chose
him compared to only 41% who voted for
Hillary Clinton. This ended up proving
to be politically decisive for Trump in
Florida and likely handed him the entire
nationwide election. Florida just barely
voted more for Trump than Hillary in
2016. With 49% of the state's overall
vote to Trump and 47.8% [music]
to Hillary, Trump only won in Florida by
a little more than 112,000 votes. Out of
more than 9 million total votes cast
nationwide, Latinos overwhelmingly voted
in favor for Hillary with 71% of their
total compared to just 28% who voted for
Trump. Cubanameans in Florida, however,
were one of the very few Latino
demographics in the country that voted
significantly more in favor of Trump
during the election instead. And had
they voted more in line with the broader
Latino community nationwide, their vote
would have shifted from plus 73,442
in favor of Trump to plus 242,921
in favor of Clinton, which in other
words would have been enough to have
shifted the entire state and all of its
29 electoral votes over to Clinton,
which would have handed the entire
general election and the presidency to
Clinton instead. So basically, the
CubanAmerican support for Trump in
Florida effectively handed him the
presidency in [music] 2016. And Trump
rewarded them for their loyalty by
immediately doing what he promised them
when he entered into office in 2017,
adopting a renewed hardline approach to
the communist regime in Cuba with the
ultimate goal of full-on regime change
and reversing all of Obama's policies
that had attempted to open up and
normalize relations with the Castros
still being in charge.
Trump immediately began restricting the
ability for Americans to travel to Cuba
again. And he eventually placed a cap on
the amount of remittances that US
citizens were able to send to Cuban
nationals. Before Trump's cap,
Cubanameans could essentially send
however much they wanted to their
relatives on the island. But Trump
capped the maximum limit to just $1,000
per [music] person per quarter or $4,000
per year instead, sharply reducing the
amount of cash inflows that were coming
to the island. Later in 2017, multiple
staff members at the US Embassy in
Havana began reporting mysterious
neurological symptoms and illnesses that
later became known simply as Havana
syndrome. No cause for Habana syndrome
has ever been publicly confirmed, but
the US government has suspected the
Cuban government of being involved. And
after the report started happening, the
State Department severely reduced their
staff at the embassy in Havana and
expelled most of the Cuban staff from
the Cuban embassy in Washington, which
essentially brought visa processing
between them to a screeching halt. By
2019, American visitors to Cuba were
blocked from staying in most hotels in
the country. Most air and cruise travel
between the countries was halted again.
Western Union was pressured into ending
their wiring services to the island, and
the Trump administration was already
attempting to interrupt Venezuela's oil
shipments to Cuba through targeted
sanctions on the carriers that were
transporting the oil. In the final days
of the first Trump administration, right
before Biden took over office, the Trump
administration also readded Cuba back to
the State Department's list of state
sponsors of terrorism. again. The most
severe consequence of which was wrecking
Cuba's ability to participate in the
international financial structures that
are dominated by the United States.
All of these renewed American sanctions
on Cuba, plus the crippling trade
embargo that had continually been in
place since the 1960s, inflicted
billions of dollars worth of damage on
the Cuban economy with the explicit
purpose of attempting to encourage
either regime change or regime
moderation on the island. And at the
same time, the CO 19 pandemic wrecked
whatever was left of Cuba's tourism
industry just after it had started
growing again during the Obama
administration. Foreign tourists to the
island plummeted from millions in 2018
and 19 to virtually nobody across 2020
and 21, costing the country billions of
additional dollars in lost tourism
revenue. And as Cuban-American families
stopped visiting because of the new
restrictions and the pandemic, the value
of their remittances also collapsed from
$3.7 billion in 2019 down to just $1.1
billion in 2021. And on top of all of
these externally induced problems, the
Cuban economy itself was still saddled
with the inefficient structural problems
that are associated with most centrally
planned economies as well. Food
production in Cuba completely collapsed
during this time period, both due to a
lack of cash for farm equipment and
fertilizer, but also because of
inefficient government set price
controls on produce that left Cuban
farmers with no real incentive to
actually work and produce. The Cuban
armed forces themselves are also known
to control a sprawling conglomerate in
the country that's best known by its
acronym GASA, which according to
reporting by the Miami Herald currently
controls at least 40% of the Cuban
economy and $18 billion worth of
secretive stashed away assets that have
been hidden from the Cuban public. Gaya
controls most of Cuba's hotels, gas
stations, supermarkets, and the whole
currency exchange business, which are
all of the most profitable industries on
the island. The Communist Party of Cuba
has long blamed all of the island's
problems on the US government and the
trade embargo. And yet, reporting by the
Miami Herald on GA's secretive
operations and assets has revealed that
they have plenty of cash on hand to
cover all of Cuba's most vital expenses,
including the $43 million that's
required per year to cover access to the
63 priority medications that have been
limited in Cuba and the $250 million per
year that's required to operate and
maintain Cuba's electricity grid. They
simply don't and have continued hoarding
the limited assets that are available in
Cuba for themselves [music] to the
detriment of everybody else who's not
closely connected to the Communist Party
itself. In the 5 years up to 2023,
Cuba's once vaunted sugar industry
collapsed by 68%.
Its fishing industry by 53%, its broader
agricultural industry by 52%, and its
manufacturing industry by 41%.
On top of the near total collapse in the
tourism industry, which Gasea had
misallocated most of their investment
capital into over more pressing
industries that could have benefited the
Cuban people more, like agriculture and
medicine. All of this, near the end of
Trump's first term, was the beginning of
Cuba's current existential crisis, as
the lack of foreign earnings led to a
collapse in the government's ability to
provide most basic services. Biden then
ran on a campaign criticizing how
Trump's policies had negatively affected
Cuban families and promised to revert
back to the Obama era of normalization
again. But then after he assumed the
presidency in 2021, he basically just
didn't do anything for years that kept
nearly all of Trump's maximum pressure
policies on the island still in place.
Wary of the outsized political influence
of the Cuban-American exile community in
South Florida that has always favored a
tough foreign policy approach to Cuba,
Biden remained fearful throughout his
presidency of doing anything much
different than Trump, lest he upset them
and risk losing Florida again in the
2024 election. Biden eliminated Trump's
restrictions on the amount of
remittances that could be sent to Cuba
and some of the travel restrictions for
US citizens, [music] but he also
maintained the first Trump
administration's designation of Cuba as
a state sponsor of terrorism, which
continued in snaring Cuba's ability to
access the global financial system. It
wasn't until Biden was imminently about
to leave the presidency on the 14th of
January, 2025, that he finally decided
to remove Cuba from the list. But it was
too little, too late. Just 6 days after
Biden did so, Trump returned back to
office for a second term and immediately
readded Cuba back to the list the very
day he assumed office. [music]
With virtually all of the Trump era
restrictions on Cuba remaining in place
throughout the Biden era and the CO 19
pandemic wrecking the island's nassent
tourism industry, Cuba was also stricken
by the crippling economic crisis in
Venezuela, which resulted in the
Venezuelans sending less and less of
their subsidized oil to Cuba's way.
Remember that as recently as 2021, the
Venezuelans were still sending Cuba
approximately 100,000 barrels of oil per
day. But by 2024, the final year of the
Biden presidency, they were only sending
Cuba about 32,000 barrels of oil per day
instead. And by 2025, it had declined
even further to just 16,000 barrels per
day, which exacerbated Cuba's shortage
of foreign exchange currency and
contributed to the increasing pace of
fuel shortages and electricity blackouts
across the island as they struggled to
find replacements willing to trade with
them in the face of the US economic and
trade embargo and sanctions regime.
Struggling to cope with the scale of all
of these crisis [music] striking the
island at the same time that were
triggering blackouts and shortages of
basic food and medicine. Largecale
anti-regime protests erupted across Cuba
over the summer of 2021 that were met by
the Communist Party with harsh
repression. Hundreds of protesters were
arrested and at least 710 of them were
later charged with crimes, including
[music] serious charges like sedition
that carried lengthy prison sentences of
up to 30 years behind bars. The scale of
the crisis, the biggest since the
collapse of the Soviet Union for the
island and the Cuban government's own
repression and crushing of descent, is
what led to the unprecedented exodus of
people away from Cuba across the 2020s.
[music] In 2020, Nicaragua significantly
loosened visa restrictions for Cuban
nationals, [music] which led to Cubans
by the hundreds of thousands taking
flights to Nicaragua and then traveling
by land north towards the US southern
border and entering throughout the Biden
administration. The latest episode in
the Cuban government's apparent
willingness to export [music] its
dissenters away from the country.
Throughout Biden's presidency, an
estimated 850,000
Cubans entered into the United States.
[music]
And then came the return of Trump again
in 2025 and the return back to his even
stricter policies on Cuba. Trump's
handpicked Secretary of State is Marco
Rubio, the son of Cuban exiles, who is
the product of South Florida's
Cuban-American exile community. He has
been a lifetime hawk on America's policy
towards the communist regime in Cuba and
his ultimate geopolitical project has
been the toppling of the communist party
from power in Cuba once and for all. As
Secretary of State, he is now the
highest ranking US government official
of Cuban ancestry in the country's
history. [music] And while
simultaneously serving as Trump's
national security adviser, he is
arguably the most powerful secretary of
state in American history since Henry
Kissinger. He is incredibly influential
in the second Trump administration
[music] and the primary force that's
driving the administration's policy
towards Cuba and showing even more
support than they did for Trump in the
previous elections in 2016 and in 2020.
Cubanameans in Florida voted even more
overwhelmingly in favor of Trump again
in 2024. despite Biden's best attempts
to appease them with 68% of their total
voting Trump, an even higher ratio than
white men who voted for Trump in 2024.
All of which has given the Trump
administration the full legitimacy to
finally attempt and accomplish the
capitalist Cuba's decadesl long dream of
toppling the communist from power in the
island of Cuba with a military operation
that ousted Maduro from Venezuela. One
of Trump and Rubio's goals has been to
eliminate the remaining trickle of oil
that was still flowing into Cuba from
the country, which will probably plunge
the island into an even greater
electricity and fuel crisis than it was
suffering before. With other countries
like Mexico and Russia unlikely to step
in and fill the gap because of political
pressure from the United States, the
pressure on Cuba is therefore still
building, but it's unclear whether or
not it'll be enough to truly crack it.
While it's also unclear if the pressure
could become too great and cause a
catastrophic state collapse scenario
like over in Haiti. Cuba is unlike
Venezuela in the sense that the
Communist Party has maintained its grip
on power in the island for nearly seven
decades now. It managed to survive the
retirement and death of Fidel Castro
when power passed to his younger brother
Raul. and he managed to survive when
Raul passed the presidency to a
handpicked successor in 2018, Miguel
Diaz Canel, who remains Cuba's current
leader and the first non-Castro head of
state since the late 1950s.
Nonetheless, Ro Castro is still alive
for the time being and maintains a
significant level of control, influence,
and power behind the scenes. At the
elderly age of 94 years old, however,
his remaining time in our world is
likely not much longer, and a potential
succession crisis behind the scenes in
the Communist Party looms once he's
gone. It remains unclear how and if
communism can continue surviving in Cuba
without the leadership of the first
generation of Castros still continuing
it. For the moment, the Trump
administration seems unwilling to use
military force in Cuba to encourage
regime change the same way they have
done so in Venezuela and the same way
they have threatened to do in Iran.
There is probably a high degree of fear
of applying too much pressure on Cuba
right now and causing it to completely
collapse in a Haiti style scenario which
would skyrocket rates of Cuban migration
to the United States even further than
it's already been these past few years
which would greatly complicate the Trump
administration's domestic migration
agenda and policy. What's most likely to
continue happening between the US and
Cuba instead is a continuation of the
decadesl long trade embargo and
financial sanctions choking Cuba's
ability to trade. A continuation of
severing Cuba's few remaining sources of
oil imports to further the
island's electricity and fuel supplies.
and a holding out for hope in Washington
that the Communist Party will eventually
agree to become pragmatic and negotiate
with the US on moderating their economic
policies and their political
authoritarianism
[music] and in so doing allowing more
private businesses access to US
companies, restoring some of the value
of expropriated assets and property over
the decades to the Cuban-American
community in South Florida and to US
businesses and releasing some political
prisoners in exchange for American 's
loosening up of the sanctions, the oil
restrictions, and the embargo terms.
[music] The Communist Party of Cuba is
currently in the most dire crisis that
it's probably ever been in. And while it
might end up finally collapsing or
relenting to America's pressure under
the weight of this crisis, like many
people have been predicting, it also
might continue defying everybody's
expectations, and [music] continue on
existing regardless, just as it somehow
managed to do so far. In a way, sort of
like North Korea, just like what
happened to Cuba in the 1990s when the
Soviet Union collapsed and lost their
primary supporter, North Korea went
through the same thing that resulted in
a deluge of expert analysis that
predicted it would result in the
country's imminent [music] collapse. And
yet, North Korea somehow kept on
surviving just like Cuba did anyway. But
if you thought that Cuba's experiences
have been catastrophic in the aftermath
of the Cold War, and they have been,
North Korea's experience in the 1990s
after losing the Soviet Union was
downright apocalyptic. For most of the
decade, the country was ravaged by one
of the worst economic collapses in
modern history that accompanied one of
the worst famines in modern history. As
well, the North Korea's centrally
planned system couldn't adequately
address. As many as 3 and 12 million
North Koreans would die during this
horrific famine throughout the 1990s. As
much as 15% of [music] the entire
country's population and all as the
government attempted everything it could
do to cover up its scale and hide it
from the rest of the world. [music]
The famine and the crisis within North
Korea throughout the 1990s was
exacerbated by the first change in
leadership in the country's history in
1994 when the Kim dynasty's founder
Kimmel Sun died after having ruled for
the past 45 years and passed on power to
his son Kim Jong-il establishing the
first dynastic succession in North
Korea. Kim Jong-il's incompetent
mismanagement of the famine greatly
exacerbated the scale of the tragedy.
And for [music] the next 17 years until
his own death, he would continue on
advancing his father's cult of
personality even further and rule North
Korea with every bit as iron of a fist.
To this date, Kim Jong-il, the middle
Kim ruler, is still officially regarded
by North Korea's legal system to be the
country's eternal general secretary.
still serving in death alongside of his
father who was similarly designated as
the eternal president upon his own
death. Kim Jong-il like his father is
still heralded as nearly a god in the
country along with his own son who would
eventually take the country over himself
in the third succession in 2011. And I
think that understanding Kim Jong-il and
how he continued molding North Korea
into the bizarre necro hereditary
dictatorship that it is today is a major
lesson in what can happen with truly
unchecked power in the modern world. And
so I made an entire new documentary
exploring the dark world and life of Kim
Jong-il and the most outlandish things
that he did while ruling North Korea for
decades in my brand new original
documentary series that I'm calling Mad
Kings, which will take deeper dives into
the terrible personal lives and erratic
policy decisions of recent
megalomaniacal and eccentric dictators.
But because of the inherently violent
and controversial details surrounding
Kim Jong-il, including details and
depictions of multiple acts of terrorism
that he ordered across the 1980s and
'90s and one of the worst famines in
human history, my documentary
investigating his reign would never
[music] work on YouTube because it would
instantly become demonetized and age
restricted, which means that YouTube's
algorithm that's based around showing
you ads would never actually be
incentivized to show the video to you or
to promote it. I deal with very large
numbers of my videos on YouTube getting
demonetized and age restricted as they
already are, including one of my more
recent videos that cover the ongoing
events taking place in Darth Fur. And
that's why I'm uploading all of my
documentaries at Mad Kings, including
this one on Kim Jong-il, exclusively to
Nebula instead. And why signing up to
Nebula is the absolute [music] best
thing that you can do to support me and
my channel. And there's never been a
better time to sign up because now you
can get 50% off of the annual
subscription for just $30 for the entire
year. And there's plenty of new content
for you to watch right now. There's
Scav, a new documentary series by the
Jetlag team that follows the world's
largest scavenger hunt. There's multiple
new exclusive video essays by Lindsay
Ellis and a new short film by Patrick
Williams called The Dinner Plan that
features Griffin Newman and Zach Cherry.
[music] And of course, Nebula is also
still home to some of the best curated
and informative documentaries available
anywhere on the internet today. There's
Bobby Broccley's 17 pages documentary
covering one of the largest scientific
controversies of the 20th century.
Realtime history 16 days in Berlin, the
most detailed Battle of Berlin
documentary ever produced. Wover
productions, the logistics of X series,
and of course my own modern conflict
series, covering dozens and dozens of
modern wars, battles, and conflicts with
plenty more originals from myself and
other creators planned throughout 2026.
[music]
I personally treat Nebula as my own
sanctuary away from the noise of
algorithmically driven sites like
YouTube and other social media. There's
no AI bots and no AI generated slop
clogging up your feed here. We choose
and vet which creators we work with and
that enables us to only work with the
best creators who truly love and take
pride in what they do. So if you want to
support me and hundreds of other
independent creators who still value our
craft and get access to some of the best
documentaries and video essays anywhere
on the internet that you won't find here
on YouTube. You can do so by visiting
the link that's down below in the
description by scanning the QR code here
on your screen or by clicking the button
that's here on your screen and signing
up. You'll get 50% off of an annual
subscription by doing so, which is just
$30 for the whole year or $250 per
month, a fraction of the price of
YouTube Premium. You can even sign up
for a lifetime membership as well with a
40% off discount for [music] $300.
If you don't ever want to deal with yet
another streaming platform subscription
or ads ever again for as long as we both
last, I hope that you'll consider
signing up or gifting to a friend or a
loved one. And as always, thank you so
much for watching.